How many of you have been to Oklahoma City?
كم شخص منكم قد زار مدينة أوكلاهوما؟
Raise your hand. Yeah?
ارفعوا أياديكم. نعم؟
How many of you have not been to Oklahoma City
كم واحد منكم لم يزر مدينة أوكلاهوما
and have no idea who I am? (Laughter)
و ليس عنده فكرة عمن أكون؟ (ضحك)
Most of you. Let me give you a little bit of background.
أغلبكم. دعني أعطيكم خلفية بسيطة.
Oklahoma City started in the most
لقد نشأت مدينة أوكلاهوما
unique way imaginable.
بطريقة فريدة جداً.
Back on a spring day in 1889,
في يوم ربيعي عام 1889،
the federal government held what they called
عقدت الحكومة الفدرالية ما أسمته
a land run.
بسباق على الأراضي.
They literally lined up the settlers
لقد قامو حرفياً بصفّ السكان
along an imaginary line,
على خط وهمي،
and they fired off a gun,
و أطلقوا النار،
and the settlers roared across the countryside
وضاج السكان في أرجاء الريف
and put down a stake,
ووضعوا وتدا،
and wherever they put down that stake,
وحيثما وضعوا هذا الوتد،
that was their new home.
أصبح منزلهم الجديد.
And at the end of the very first day,
وفي نهاية اليوم الأول،
the population of Oklahoma City
ارتفع عدد سكان مدينة أوكلاهوما
had gone from zero to 10,000,
من صفر إلى 10,000،
and our planning department
ولا يزال قسم التخطيط لدينا
is still paying for that.
يتحمل عواقب ذلك.
The citizens got together on that first day
اجتمع السكان في ذلك اليوم
and elected a mayor.
وانتخبوا عمدة.
And then they shot him.
وثم أطلقوا عليه النار.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's not really all that funny
إن الأمر ليس مضحكا جداً
-- (Laughter) --
-- (ضحك) --
but it allows me to see what type of audience
لكنه جعلني أرى نوع الجمهور
I'm dealing with, so I appreciate the feedback.
الذي أتعامل معه، لذا إنني أقدر ردة الفعل.
The 20th century was fairly kind to Oklahoma City.
لقد كان القرن الـ 20 لطيفا جداً على مدينة أوكلاهوما.
Our economy was based on commodities,
لقد كان اقتصادنا قائماً على البضائع،
so the price of cotton or the price of wheat,
على قيمة القطن أو قيمة القمح،
and ultimately the price of oil and natural gas.
والأهم هو قيمة النفط والغاز الطبيعي.
And along the way, we became a city
وخلال الوقت، أصبحنا مدينة
of innovation.
الابتكارات.
The shopping cart was invented in Oklahoma City.
إن عربة التسوّق تم اخراعها في مدينة أوكلاهوما.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The parking meter, invented in Oklahoma City.
لقد اخترع عدّاد موقف السيارات في مدينة أوكلاهوما.
You're welcome.
لا شكر على واجب.
Having an economy, though,
لكن، عندما يكون لديك اقتصاد
that relates to commodities can give you some ups and some downs,
قائم على البضائع فهو لا يكون مستقرا،
and that was certainly the case in Oklahoma City's history.
وهذا حقاً ما حصل في تاريخ مدينة أوكلاهوما.
In the 1970s, when it appeared
في السبعينات، عندما بدا
that the price of energy would never retreat,
أن سعر الطاقة لن يتراجع أبداً،
our economy was soaring,
كان اقتصادنا يحلّق،
and then in the early 1980s, it cratered quickly.
وثم في بداية الثمانينات، انحدر بسرعة.
The price of energy dropped.
لقد انخفض سعر الطاقة.
Our banks began to fail.
وبدأت بنوكنا بالإفلاس.
Before the end of the decade,
وقبل نهاية العقد،
100 banks had failed in the state of Oklahoma.
كان قد أفلس 100 بنك في ولاية أوكلاهوما.
There was no bailout on the horizon.
لم يبدوا أنه هناك فرج في المدى الطويل.
Our banking industry, our oil and gas industry,
كانت صناعة البنوك، صناعة النفط والغاز،
our commercial real estate industry,
صناعة العقارات التجارية،
were all at the bottom of the economic scale.
كلها في أدنى مرتبة على المقياس الاقتصادي.
Young people were leaving Oklahoma City in droves
كان الشباب يرحلون من مدينة أوكلاهوما في مجموعات
for Washington and Dallas and Houston and New York and Tokyo,
إلى واشنطن ودالاس وهيوستن ونيويورك وطوكيو،
anywhere where they could find a job that measured up
إلى أي مكان حيث أمكنهم إيجاد عمل يناسب
to their educational attainment,
مستواهم التعليمي،
because in Oklahoma City, the good jobs just weren't there.
لأنه في مدينة أوكلاهوما لم تكن هناك وظائف جيدة.
But along at the end of the '80s
لكن مع نهاية الثمانينات
came an enterprising businessman
جاء رجل أعمال مغامر
who became mayor named Ron Norick.
الذي أصبح العمدة، اسمه رون نوريك.
Ron Norick eventually figured out
رون نوريك قد استنتج
that the secret to economic development
أن السر للتطور الاقتصادي
wasn't incentivizing companies up front,
لم يكن بتحفيز الشركات مقدماً،
it was about creating a place where businesses wanted to locate,
إنه بإنشاء مكان حيث تريد الشركات أن تتمركز،
and so he pushed an initiative called MAPS
وهكذا لقد دفع بمبادرة اسمها إم أي بي أس
that basically was a penny-on-the-dollar sales tax
التي كانت عبارة عن ضريبة شراء بمقدار بنس لكل دولار
to build a bunch of stuff.
لبناء عدة أشياء.
It built a new sports arena,
لقد تم بناء بأموال الضرائب حلبة رياضية جديدة،
a new canal downtown,
قناة جديدة في وسط المدينة،
it fixed up our performing arts center,
لقد تم إصلاح مركز الفنون المسرحية،
a new baseball stadium downtown,
ملعب كرة مضرب جديد في وسط المدينة،
a lot of things to improve the quality of life.
العديد من الأشياء لتحسين مستوى المعيشة.
And the economy indeed seemed to start
وبدأ الاقتصاد حقاً
showing some signs of life.
بإبداء بعض مؤشرات الحياة.
The next mayor came along.
ثم جاء العمدة التالي.
He started MAPS for Kids,
لقد قام ببرنامج أم أي بي إس للأطفال،
rebuilt the entire inner city school system,
أعاد بناء نظام مدارس المدينة المحلي بأكمله،
all 75 buildings either built anew or refurbished.
جميع الأبنية الـ 75 إما تم إعادة بناؤها من جديد أو تجديدها.
And then, in 2004,
وثم، في عام 2004،
in this rare collective lack of judgment
في غياب الحكم الجماعي نادر الحدوث هذا
bordering on civil disobedience,
القريب من العصيان المدني،
the citizens elected me mayor.
اختارني السكان عمدة.
Now the city I inherited
الآن إن المدينة التي ورثتها
was just on the verge
تكاد تكون على حافة
of coming out of its slumbering economy,
الخروج من اقتصادها الراكد،
and for the very first time,
ولأول مرة،
we started showing up on the lists.
بدأنا بالظهور على القوائم.
Now you know the lists I'm talking about.
الآن أنتم تعرفوا القوائم التي أتحدث عنها.
The media and the Internet
إن الإعلام والانترنت
love to rank cities.
يحبان تقييم المدن.
And in Oklahoma City,
وفي مدينة أوكلاهوما،
we'd never really been on lists before.
لم نكن قد ظهرنا أبدأ على قائمة من قبل.
So I thought it was kind of cool
لذا اعتقدت أن الأمر رائع نوع ما
when they came out with these positive lists and we were on there.
عندما بدؤوا بهذه القوائم الإيجابية وكنا نحن عليها.
We weren't anywhere close to the top,
لم نكن قريبين من أعلى القائمة،
but we were on the list, we were somebody.
لكن كنا على القائمة، لقد كان لنا اعتبارنا.
Best city to get a job,
أفضل مدينة للحصول على وظيفة،
best city to start a business,
أفضل مدينة لبدء تجارة،
best downtown --
أفضل وسط مدينة --
Oklahoma City.
مدينة أوكلاهوما.
And then came the list
ثم ظهرت قائمة
of the most obese cities in the country.
أكثر مدن الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية سمنة.
And there we were.
وكنا عليها.
Now I like to point out that we were on that list
الآن أود أن أشير إلى أننا كنا على تلك القائمة
with a lot of really cool places.
مع العديد من الأماكن الممتعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Dallas and Houston and New Orleans
دالاس وهيوستن ونيوأورلينز
and Atlanta and Miami.
وأتلانتا وميامي.
You know, these are cities that, typically,
أتعلمون، هذه مدن، بالعادة،
you're not embarrassed to be associated with.
لا تشعرك بالإحراج لارتباطك بها.
But nonetheless, I didn't like being on the list.
لكن بالرغم من ذلك، لم أحب كوننا على القائمة.
And about that time, I got on the scales.
وخلال ذلك الوقت، صعدت على الميزان.
And I weighed 220 pounds.
وكان وزني 220 رطلا.
And then I went to this website
ثم زرت هذا الموقع
sponsored by the federal government,
الذي ترعاه الحكومة الفيدرالية،
and I typed in my height, I typed in my weight,
وأدخلت طولي، أدخلت وزني،
and I pushed Enter,
وضغطت مفتاح أدخل،
and it came back and said "obese."
وظهر لي رسالة تقول: "سمين".
I thought, "What a stupid website."
فكرت: "يا لغباء هذا الموقع."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I'm not obese. I would know if I was obese."
"أنا لست سمينا. كنت لأعلم إن كنت سمين."
And then I started getting honest with myself
و ثم بدأت أن أكون صادقاً مع ذاتي
about what had become my lifelong struggle with obesity,
بخصوص ما أصبح صراعي المستمر مع السمنة،
and I noticed this pattern,
ولاحظت النمط التالي،
that I was gaining about two or three pounds a year,
كنت أكتسب حوالي رطلين أو ثلاثة كل سنة،
and then about every 10 years, I'd drop 20 or 30 pounds.
ثم بعد حوالي كل 10 سنوات، كنت أخسر 20 أو 30 رطل.
And then I'd do it again.
وثم أكرر الأمر.
And I had this huge closet full of clothes,
وكانت لدي هذه الخزانة الهائلة المليئة بالملابس،
and I could only wear a third of it at any one time,
وكنت قادرا على ارتداء فقط ثلث ما فيها في أي وقت،
and only I knew which part of the closet I could wear.
وكنت أنا الوحيد الذي يعلم أي جزء من الخزانة أستطيع ارتداءه.
But it all seemed fairly normal, going through it.
لكن بدا الأمر كله طبيعيا جداً، مروري بهذا.
Well, I finally decided I needed to lose weight,
حسناً، في النهاية قررت أنه يجب علي أن أخسر وزن،
and I knew I could because I'd done it so many times before,
وعلمت أنه كان بوسعي ذلك لأني قمت بالأمر العديد من المرات في السابق،
so I simply stopped eating as much.
لذا ببساطة توقفت عن أكل نفس الكميات.
I had always exercised.
لقد كنت دائم التمرن.
That really wasn't the part of the equation
هذا لم يكن حقاً جزء من الحل
that I needed to work on.
أنه يجب علي أن أتمرن.
But I had been eating 3,000 calories a day,
لكنني كنت آكل 3,000 سعرة حرارية في اليوم،
and I cut it to 2,000 calories a day,
وقلصتها إلى 2,000 سعرة حرارية في اليوم،
and the weight came off. I lost about a pound a week
وخسرت الوزن. خسرت حوالي رطلا في الأسبوع
for about 40 weeks.
لحوالي 40 أسبوعاً.
Along the way, though,
لكني خلال ذلك،
I started examining my city,
بدأت بدراسة مدينتي،
its culture, its infrastructure,
ثقافتها وبنيتها التحتية،
trying to figure out why our specific city
محاولاً فهم لماذا مدينتنا بالتحديد
seemed to have a problem with obesity.
يبدو أنها تعاني مع السمنة.
And I came to the conclusion
واستنتجت
that we had built an incredible quality of life
أننا قمنا بتوفير رفاهية لا تصدق
if you happen to be a car.
إن كنت سيارة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But if you happen to be a person,
لكن إن كنت إنسانا،
you are combatting the car seemingly at every turn.
فإنك تحارب السيارة طوال الوقت.
Our city is very spread out.
إن مدينتنا واسعة جداً.
We have a great intersection of highways,
لدينا تقاطع كبير للطرق السريعة،
I mean, literally no traffic congestion in Oklahoma City to speak of.
أعني، لا توجد اختناقات مرورية حرفياً يمكن الحديث عنها في مدينة أوكلاهوما.
And so people live far, far away.
لذا يعيش الناس في أماكن بعيدة جداً، جداً.
Our city limits are enormous, 620 square miles,
إن حدود مدينتنا هائلة، 620 ميل مربع،
but 15 miles is less than 15 minutes.
لكن 15 ميل في أقل من 15 دقيقة.
You literally can get a speeding ticket
هناك قابلية أن تحصل على مخالفة
during rush hour in Oklahoma City.
خلال ساعة الذروة في مدينة أوكلاهوما.
And as a result, people tend to spread out.
وكنتيجة لذلك، يميل الناس إلى الانتشار.
Land's cheap.
إن الأرض رخيصة.
We had also not required developers
نحن أيضاً لم نطلب من المطورين
to build sidewalks on new developments for a long, long time.
بناء أرصفة في التطويرات الجديدة منذ زمن بعيد جداً، جداً.
We had fixed that, but it had been relatively recently,
لقد أصلحنا ذلك، لكن الأمر حديث نسبياً
and there were literally 100,000
وكان هناك حرفياً 100,000 منزل
or more homes into our inventory
أو أكثر في الجرد الذي قمنا به
in neighborhoods that had virtually no level of walkability.
في أحياء لم يكن لها واقعياً أي طريق للمشي.
And as I tried to examine
وبينما حاولت دراسة
how we might deal with obesity,
كيف يمكننا التعامل مع السمنة،
and was taking all of these elements into my mind,
وكنت آخذ كل هذه العوامل في عين الاعتبار،
I decided that the first thing we need to do
قررت أن أول شيء يجب علينا فعله
was have a conversation.
كان بدء حوار.
You see, in Oklahoma City,
كما ترون، في مدينة أوكلاهوما،
we weren't talking about obesity.
نحن لم نكن نتكلم عن السمنة.
And so, on New Year's Eve of 2007,
وهكذا، في ليلة رأس السنة لعام 2007،
I went to the zoo,
ذهبت إلى حديقة الحيوان،
and I stood in front of the elephants,
ووقفت أمام الفيلة،
and I said, "This city is going on a diet,
وقلت: "سوف تتبع هذه المدينة حمية،
and we're going to lose a million pounds."
وسوف نخسر مليون رطل."
Well, that's when all hell broke loose.
حسناً، هنا حيث انقلبت الدنيا رأساً على عقب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The national media
الإعلام الوطني
gravitated toward this story immediately,
انجذب نحو هذه القصة على الفور،
and they really could have gone with it one of two ways.
وحقاً كانت هناك وجهتان لعرض القصة.
They could have said,
كان بإمكانهم القول:
"This city is so fat
"هذه المدينة سمينة جداً
that the mayor had to put them on a diet."
لدرجة أنه كان على العمدة جعل الناس تتبع حمية."
But fortunately, the consensus was,
لكن لحسن الحظ، الإجماع كان على التالي:
"Look, this is a problem in a lot of places.
"انظروا، إن هذه مشكلة شائعة.
This is a city that's wanting to do something about it."
هذه مدينة تريد فعل شيء حيال الأمر."
And so they started helping us
وهكذا بدؤوا بمساعدتنا
drive traffic to the website.
على جذب المزيد من الناس إلى صفحتنا الالكترونية.
Now, the web address was
الآن، كان عنوان الموقع هو
thiscityisgoingonadiet.com.
thiscityisgoingonadiet.com [هذه المدينة سوف تتبع حمية].
And I appeared on "The Ellen DeGeneres Show"
وظهرت في برنامج "إلين ديجينيريس"
one weekday morning to talk about the initiative,
في صباح أحد الأيام للحديث عن هذه المبادرة،
and on that day, 150,000 visits
وفي ذلك اليوم، 150,000 شخص
were placed to our website.
زار موقعنا.
People were signing up,
الناس كانت تسجل في الموقع،
and so the pounds started to add up,
وهكذا بدأت الأرطال بالزيادة،
and the conversation that I thought
وبدأ الحوار الذي اعتقدت
was so important to have was starting to take place.
أنه من مهم جداً أن يدور.
It was taking place inside the homes,
لقد كان يدور في المنازل،
mothers and fathers talking about it with their kids.
أمهات وآباء يتكلمون عنه مع أطفالهم.
It was taking place in churches.
لقد كان يدور في الكنائس.
Churches were starting their own running groups
كانت الكنائس تقيم مجموعات جري خاصة بها
and their own support groups
ومجموعات دعم خاصة بها
for people who were dealing with obesity.
للأشخاص الذين يواجهون السمنة.
Suddenly, it was a topic worth discussing at schools
فجأة، لقد أصبح موضوع يستحق المناقشة في المدارس
and in the workplace.
وفي أماكن العمل.
And the large companies, they typically have
وتمتلك الشركات الكبرى في العادة
wonderful wellness programs,
برامج صحة رائعة،
but the medium-sized companies
لكن الشركات المتوسطة
that typically fall between the cracks on issues like this,
التي تتجاهل في العادة قضايا كهذه،
they started to get engaged and used our program
بدأت بالمشاركة واستخدمت برنامجنا
as a model for their own employees
كنموذج لموظفيها
to try and have contests to see
لمحاولة القيام بمسابقات لمعرفة
who might be able to deal with their obesity situation
من قد يكون بإمكانه أن يتعامل مع حالة السمنة التي لديهم
in a way that could be proactively beneficial to others.
بأسلوب يمكنه أن يكون مفيد بطريقة استباقية للآخرين.
And then came the next stage of the equation.
ثم حان وقت المرحلة التالية من المعادلة.
It was time to push what I called MAPS 3.
لقد حان الوقت للدفع بالمرحلة الثالثة لبرنامج إم أي بي إس.
Now MAPS 3, like the other two programs,
الآن، برنامج إم أي بي إس الثالث، كالبرنامجين الآخرين،
had had an economic development motive behind it,
كان التطور الاقتصادي هو الدافع من ورائه،
but along with the traditional economic development tasks
لكن مع مهام التطور الاقتصادي التقليدية
like building a new convention center,
كبناء مركز اجتماعات،
we added some health-related infrastructure
لقد أضفنا بعض البنية التحتية المرتبطة بالصحة
to the process.
إلى العملية.
We added a new central park, 70 acres in size,
لقد أضفنا حديقة مركزية جديدة، مساحتها 70 فدان،
to be right downtown in Oklahoma City.
لكي تكون تماماً في وسط المدينة في مدينة أوكلاهوما.
We're building a downtown streetcar
إننا نقوم بإنشاء ترام لوسط المدينة
to try and help the walkability formula
للمساعدة على المشي
for people who choose to live in the inner city
للأشخاص الذين يختارون العيش في داخل المدينة
and help us create the density there.
ولمساعدتنا على تركيز الكثافة هناك.
We're building senior health and wellness centers
إننا نبني مراكز صحة للمسنين ومراكز صحية
throughout the community.
في جميع أنحاء المجتمع.
We put some investments on the river
لقد استثمرنا في النهر
that had originally been invested upon
الذي تم الاستثمار فيه بالأصل
in the original MAPS,
في برامج الـ إم أي بي إس الأول،
and now we are currently in the final stages
والآن نحن في المراحل النهائية
of developing the finest venue in the world
لتطوير أرقى مكان في العالم
for the sports of canoe, kayak and rowing.
لرياضات قوارب الكانو والكاياك والتجديف.
We hosted the Olympic trials last spring.
لقد استضفنا تجارب الألعاب الأولمبية في الربيع الفائت.
We have Olympic-caliber events coming to Oklahoma City,
سوف نستضيف فعاليات ضبط الألعاب الأولمبية في مدينة أوكلاهوما،
and athletes from all over the world moving in,
وسوف يأتي رياضيون من جميع أنحاء العالم،
along with inner city programs
مع برامج المدينة المحلية
to get kids more engaged in these types of recreational activities
لجعل الأطفال أكثر تفاعلاً مع هذه الأنواع من الأنشطة الترفيهية
that are a little bit nontraditional.
التي هي ليست تقليدية قليلاً.
We also, with another initiative that was passed,
نحن أيضاً، مع مبادرة أخرى تم طرحها،
are building hundreds of miles of new sidewalks
سوف نبني المئات من الأميال من الأرصفة
throughout the metro area.
على طول منطقة الميترو.
We're even going back into some
نحن أيضاً سوف نرجع
inner city situations
إلى حالات في داخل المدينة
where we had built neighborhoods
حيث قمنا ببناء أحياء سكنية
and we had built schools
وببناء مدارس
but we had not connected the two.
لكننا لم نقم بربط الإثنين.
We had built libraries and we had built neighborhoods,
لقد بنينا مكتبات و بنينا أحياء سكنية،
but we had never really connected the two
لكننا لم نصلها مع بعض أبداً
with any sort of walkability.
بأي نوع من الطرق للمشي.
Through yet another funding source,
وبواسطة مصدر تمويل آخر،
we're redesigning all of our inner city streets
سوف نعيد تصميم كل شوارع مدينتنا الداخلية
to be more pedestrian-friendly.
لكي تصبح عملية أكثر للمشاة.
Our streets were really wide,
كانت شوارعنا عريضة حقاً،
and you'd push the button to allow you to walk across,
وكان عليك الضعط على الزر لكي تستطيع العبور،
and you had to run in order to get there in time.
ويجب عليك أن تركض لكي تصل إلى هناك قبل نفاذ الوقت.
But now we've narrowed the streets,
لكنا الآن لقد ضيقنا الشوارع،
highly landscaped them, making them more pedestrian-friendly,
أعدنا تخطيطها، جعلناها أكثر عملية للمشاة،
really a redesign, rethinking the way
إنها بالفعل إعادة تصميم، تجديد للطريقة التي نفكر فيها
we build our infrastructure,
عند بناء بنيتنا التحتية،
designing a city around people and not cars.
تصميم مدينة محورها الناس وليس السيارات.
We're completing our bicycle trail master plan.
إننا نكمل الخطة الرئيسية لخط الدراجات الهوائية.
We'll have over 100 miles
سوف يكون لدينا اكثر من 100 ميل
when we're through building it out.
عندما ننتهي من إنشائه.
And so you see this culture starting to shift
وهكذا ترى بداية تغير هذه الثقافة
in Oklahoma City.
في مدينة أوكلاهوما.
And lo and behold, the demographic changes
ولاحظوا كيف أن التغيرات الديموغرافية
that are coming with it are very inspiring.
الحاصلة مع التغيير، ملهمة جداً.
Highly educated twentysomethings
إن الشباب المتعلمون في العشرينات من عمرهم
are moving to Oklahoma City from all over the region
ينتقلون إلى مدينة أوكلاهوما من جميع أنحاء المنطقة
and, indeed, even from further away, in California.
وبالفعل، حتى من المناطق البعيدة، من كاليفورنيا.
When we reached a million pounds,
عندما حققنا مليون رطل،
in January of 2012,
في يناير 2012،
I flew to New York with some our participants
سافرت إلى نيويورك مع بعض مشاركينا
who had lost over 100 pounds,
الذين خسروا أكثر من 100 رطل،
whose lives had been changed,
والذين قد تغيرت حياتهم،
and we appeared on the Rachael Ray show,
وظهرنا في برنامج ريتشال راي،
and then that afternoon, I did a round of media in New York
وحينها في تلك الظهيرة، قمت بجولة على وسائل الإعلام في نيويورك
pushing the same messages
مروجاً للرسائل نفسها
that you're accustomed to hearing about obesity and the dangers of it.
التي أنت معتاد على سماعها عن السمنة و مخاطرها.
And I went into the lobby of Men's Fitness magazine,
وذهبت إلى ردهة مجلة مينز فيتنس [صحة الرجال]،
the same magazine that had put us on that list
المجلة نفسها التي وضعتنا على تلك القائمة
five years before.
خمسة سنوات مضت.
And as I'm sitting in the lobby waiting to talk to the reporter,
وببينما كنت أجلس في الردهة أنتظر أن أتحدث مع الصحفي،
I notice there's a magazine copy
لاحظت أنه هناك نسخة من المجلة
of the current issue right there on the table,
للعدد الحالي على الطاولة هناك بالضبط،
and I pick it up, and I look at the headline
وحملتها، ونظرت إلى العنوان
across the top, and it says,
في الأعلى، ويقول:
"America's Fattest Cities: Do You Live in One?"
"أكثر مدن أمريكا سمنة، هل أنت تعيش في أحدها؟"
Well, I knew I did,
حسناً، عرفت أنني كنت أعيش في واحدة منها،
so I picked up the magazine
لذا حملت المجلة
and I began to look,
وبدأت في النظر،
and we weren't on it.
ولم نكن على القائمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Then I looked on the list of fittest cities,
وثم نظرت إلى قائمة أكثر المدن صحة،
and we were on that list.
وكنا على تلك القائمة.
We were on the list as the 22nd fittest city in the United States.
كنا المدينة الـ 22 الأكثر صحة في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
Our state health statistics are doing better.
إن إحصائيات الصحة في ولايتنا تتحسن.
Granted, we have a long way to go.
بالطبع، أمامنا طريق طويل.
Health is still not something
إن الصحة ليست أمراً
that we should be proud of in Oklahoma City,
يجب أن نفخر به في مدينة أوكلاهوما،
but we seem to have turned the cultural shift
لكن يبدو أننا قد نجحنا في التغيير الثقافي
of making health a greater priority.
لجعل الصحة ذات أولية أكبر.
And we love the idea of the demographics
ونحن نحب فكرة الإحصائيات الديموغرافية
of highly educated twentysomethings,
المتعلقة بالشباب المتعلم في العشرينيات من عمره،
people with choices, choosing Oklahoma City
الأشخاص أصحاب الخيارات الذين يختارون مدينة أوكلاهوما
in large numbers.
بأعداد كبيرة.
We have the lowest unemployment in the United States,
لدينا أقل نسبة بطالة في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
probably the strongest economy in the United States.
والاقتصاد الأقوى على الأغلب في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
And if you're like me, at some point
وإن كنت مثلي، فإنه في مرحلة معينة
in your educational career,
في مهنتك التعليمية،
you were asked to read a book called
قد طُلب منك أن تقرأ كتاب عنوانه
"The Grapes of Wrath."
"عناقيد الغضب."
Oklahomans leaving for California
حيث ينتقل سكان أوكلاهوما إلى كاليفورنيا
in large numbers for a better future.
بأعداد كبيرة من أجل مستقبل أفضل.
When we look at the demographic shifts
عندما ننظر إلى التغيرات في الإحصائيات الديموغرافية
of people coming from the west,
للأشخاص القادمين من الغرب،
it appears that what we're seeing now
يتبين أنه ما نراه الآن
is the wrath of grapes.
هو غضب العناقيد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The grandchildren are coming home.
إن الأحفاد يعودون إلى الوطن.
You've been a great audience and very attentive.
لقد كنتم جمهوراً رائعاً و نبيهاً جداً.
Thank you very much for having me here.
شكراً جزيلاً على استضافتكم لي هنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)